The Story Behind The Story
by Kenneth Blanchard, PH.D.

I am thrilled to be telling you "the story behind the story" of Who Moved My Cheese?
because it means the book has now been written, and is available for all of us read, enjoy
and share with others. This is something I've wanted to see happen ever since i first heard
Spencer Johnson tell his great "Cheese" story, year ago, before we wrote our book The One Minute Manager together.
I remember thinking then how good the stort was and how helpful it would be to me from that moment on.
Who Moved My Cheese? is a story about change that takes place in a Maze where four amusing characters look for "Cheese"
cheese being a metaphor for what we want to have in life, whether it is a job, a relationship, money, a big house, freedom,
health, recognition, spirtual peace or even an activity like jogging or golf. Each of us has our own idea of what Cheese is,
and we pursue it because we believe it makes us happy. If we get it, or it's taken away, it can be traumatic.
  
The "Maze" in the story represents where you spend time looking for what you want. It can be the organi-zation you work in,
the community you live in, or the relationships you have in your life. I tell the Cheese story that you are about to read in my talks
around the world, and often hear later from people about what a difference it has made to them.
Believe it or not, this little story has been credited with improving careers, marriages and lives!
One of the many real-life examples comes from Charlie Jones, a well-respected broadcaster for NBC-TV, who revealed that hearing the story of
Who Moved My cheese? saved his career. His job as a broadcaster is unique, but the principles he learned can be by anyone.
Here's what happened: Charlie had worked hard and had done a great job of broadcasting Track and Field events at an earlier Olympic Games, so he
was surprised and upset when his boss told him he'd been removed from these showcase events for the next Olympics and assigned to Swimming and
Diving. 
Not knowing these sports as well, he was frustrated. He felt unappreciated and he became angry. He said he felt it wasn't fair! His anger began to affect everything he did.
Rhen, he heard the story of Who Moved My Cheese?
After that he said he laughed at himself and changed his attitude. He realized his boss had just "moved his Cheese." So he adapted. He learned the two new sports, and in the process, found that
doing something new made him feel young.
It wasn't lone before his boss recognized his new attitude and energy, and he soon got better assignments. He went on to enjoy more success than ever and was later inducted into Pro Football's
Hall of Fame-Broadcasters' Alleys. That's just one of the many real-life stories I've heard about the impact this story has had on people-form their work life to their love life.
I'm such a strong believer in the power of Who Moved My Cheese? that I gave a copy of an early pre-publication edition to everyone (more than 200 people) working with our company.
Why?
Because like every company that wants to not only survive in the future but stay competitive, The Ken Blanchard Companies are constantly changing. They keep moving our "Cheese." While in the past
we may have wanted layal employees, today we need flexible people who are not possessive about "the way things are done arond here."
And yet, as you Know, living constant white water with the changes occurring all the time at work or in life can be stressful, unless people have a way of looking at chane that helps them understand it.
Enter the cheese story. When I told people about the story and then they got to read Who Moved My Cheese? you could almost feel the release of negative energy beginning to occur. Person after person form
every department went out of their way to thank me for the book and told me how helpful it had been to them already in seeing the changes going on in our company in a different light. Believe me, this brief parable
takes little time to read, but its impact can be profound. As you turn the pages, you will find three sections in this book. In the first, A Gathering, former classmates talk at a  class reunion about trying to deal with the 
changes happening in their lives. The second section is The Story of Who Moved My Cheese?, which is the core of the book. 
In The Story you will see that the two mice do better when they are faced with change because they keep things simple, while the two Lirrlepeople's complex brains and human emotions complicate things. It is not
that mice are smarter. We all know people are more intelligent than mice.
However, as you watch what the four characters do, and realize both the mice and the Littlepeople represent parts of ourselves- the simple and the complex-you can see it would be to our advantage to do simple things that
work when things change. In the third section, A Discussion, people discuss what The Story meant to them and how they are going to use it in their work and in their lives.
Some readers of this book's early manuscript preferred to step at the end of The Story, without reading further, and interpret its meaning for themselves. Others enjoyed reading A Discussion that follows because it stimulated their
thinking about how they might apply what they'd learned to their own situation. Everyone knows that not all change is good or even necessary. But in a world that is constantly changing, it is to our advantage to learn how to adapt
and enjoy something better. In any case, I hope each time you re-read Who Moved My Cheese? you will find something new and useful in the brief story, as I do, and that it will help you deal with change and bring you success, whatever
you decide success is for you. I hope you enjoy what you discover, and I wish you well. Remember: Move with the Cheese! 

ken Blanchard
San Diego, California

A gathering Chicago
One sunny Sunday in Chicago, several former classmates, who were good friends in school, gathered for lunch, having attended their high school reunion the night before. They wanted to hear more about what was happening in each other's lives.
After a good settled into an interesting conversation. Angela, who had been one of the most popular people in the class, said "Life sure turned out differently than I thought ir would when we were in school. A lot has changed."
"It cerainly has," Nathan echoed. They knew he had gone into his family's business, which had operated pertty much the same and had been a part of the local community for as long as they could remember. So, they were surprised whan he seemed concerned.
He asked, "But, have you noticed how we don't want to change when things change?" 

Carols said "I guess we resist changing because we're afaid of change." "Carlos, you were Captain of the football team," Jessia said. "I naver thought I'd hear you say anything about being afraid!" They all laughed as they realized that althouah they had
gone off in different firections-from working at home to managing companies-they were experiencing similar feelings.
Everyone was trying to cope with the unexpected changes that were happening to them in recent years. And most admitted that they did not know a good way to handle them. Then Michael said, "I used to be afraid of change. When a big change came along in our business, 
we didn't know what to do. So we didn't adjust and we almost lost it.
"That is," he continued, "until I heard a funny little story that changed everything." "How so?" Nathan asked. "Well, the story changed the way I looked at change-from losing something to gaining some-thing-and it showed me how to do it.
After that, things quickly improved-at work and in my life. "At first I was annoyed with the obvious simplicity of the story because it sounded like something we might have been told in school. "Then I realized I was really annoyed with myself for not seeing the
obvious and doing what works when things change. 
"When I reaized the four characters in the story represented the various parts of myself, I decided who I wanted to act like and I changed. "Later, I passed the story on to some people in our company and they passed it on to others, and soon our business did much better,
because most of us adapted to change batter. And like me, many people said it helped them in their personal lives. "However there were a few people who said they got nothing out of it. They either knew the lessons and were already living them, or, more commonly,
they thought they already knew everything and didn't wont to learn. They couldn't see why so many others were benefitting from it. "When one of our senior executives, who was having difficulty adapthing, said the story was a waste of time, other people kidded him saying
they knew which character he was in the story-meaning the one who learned nothing new and did not change." "What's the story?" Angela asked. "It's called, Who Moved My Cheese?" Carlos said. "Would you tell us the story? Maybe we can get something from it."
"Sure," Michael replied. "I'd be happy to- it doesn't take long." And so he began:

Who Moved My Cheese?:The Story
ONCE, long ago in a land far away, there lived four little characters who ran through a Maze looking for cheese to nourish them and make them happy. Two were mice, named "Sniff" and "Scurry" and two were Littlepeople-beings who were as small as mice but who looked and acted
a lot like people today. Their names were "Hem" and "Haw." Due to their small size, it would ne easy not to notice what the four of them were doing. But if you looked closely enough, you could discover the most amazing things!

Every day the mice and the Littlepeople spent time in the Maze looking for their own special cheese. The mice, Sniff and Scurry, possessing simple brains and good instincts, searched for the hard nibbling cheese they liked, as mice often do.
The two Littepeople, Hem and Haw, used their complex brains, filled with many beliefs and emotions, to search for a very different kind of Cheese-with a capital C-which they believed would make them feel happy and successful.
As different as the mice and Littlepeople were, they shared something in common: every morning, they each put on their jogging suits and running shoes, left their little homes, and raced out into the Maze looking for their favorite cheese.
The Maze was a labyrinth of corridors and chambers, some containing delicious cheese. But there were also dark corners and blind alleys leading nowhere. It was an easy place for anyone to get lost.

However, the two littlepeople, Hem and Haw, used a different method that relied ontheir ability to think and learn from their past experiences, although, they wouldsometimes get confused by their beliefs and emotions. Eventually in their own way, they all discovered what they were looking for – theyeach found their own kind of cheese one day at the end of one of the corridors inCheese Station C.Every morning after that, the mice and the littlepeople dressed in their running gearand headed over to Cheese Station C. It wasn’t long before they each established theirown routine. Sniff and Scurry continued to wake early every day and race through the maze,always following the same route. When they arrived at their destination, the mice took off their running shoes, tiedthem together and hung them around their necks – so they could get to them quicklywhenever they needed them again. Then they enjoyed the cheese.


In the beginning Hem and Haw also raced toward Cheese Station C every morning to enjoy the tasty new morsels that awaited them. But after a while, a different routine set in for the littlepeople. Hem and Haw awoke each day a little later, dressed a little slower, and walked toCheese Station C. After all, they knew where the Cheese was now and how to getthere.They had no idea where the Cheese came from, or who put it there. They just assumedit would be there.As soon as Hem and Haw arrived at Cheese Station C each morning, they settled inand made themselves at home. They hung up their jogging shoes and out on theirslippers. They were becoming very comfortable now that they had found the Cheese.“This is great,” Hem said. “There’s enough Cheese here to last us forever.” Thelittlepeople felt happy and successful, and thought they were secure.It wasn’t long before Hem and Haw regarded the Cheese they found at Cheese StationC as their cheese. It was such a large store of Cheese that they eventually moved theirhomes to be closer to it, and built a social life around it.To make themselves feel more at home, Hem and Haw decorated the walls withsayings and even pictures of Cheese around them which made them smile. One read: Having Cheese Makes You Happy.


Sometimes Hem and Haw would take their friends by in to see their pile of Cheese atCheese Station C, and point to it with pride, saying, “Pretty nice Cheese, huh?”Sometimes they shared it with their friends and sometimes they didn’t.“We deserve this Cheese,” Hem said. “We certainly had to work long and hardenough to find it.” He picked up a nice fresh piece and ate it.Afterwards, Hem fell asleep, as he often did.Every night the littlepeople would waddle home, full of Cheese, and every morningthey would confidently return for more.This went on for quite some time.After a while Hem’s and Haw’s confidence grew into arrogance. Soon they became socomfortable they didn’t even notice what was happening.As time went on, Sniff and Scurry continued their routine. They arrived early eachmorning and sniffed and scratched and scurried around Cheese Station C, inspectingthe area to see if there had been any changes from the day before. Then they would sitdown to nibble on the cheese.One morning they arrived at Cheese Station C and discovered there was no cheese.They weren’t surprised. Since Sniff and Scurry had noticed the supply of cheese hadbeen getting smaller every day, they were prepared for the inevitable and knewinstinctively what to do.They looked at each other, removed the running shoes they had tied together and hungconveniently around their necks, put them on their feet and laced them up.The mice did not overanalyze things. And they were not burdened with manycomplex beliefs.To the mice, the problem and the answer were both simple. The situation at CheeseStation C had changed. So, Sniff and Scurry decided to change.They both looked out into the maze. Then Sniff lifted his nose, sniffed, and nodded toScurry, who took off running through the maze, while Sniff followed as fast as hecould.They were quickly off in search of New Cheese.Later that same day, Hem and Haw arrived at Cheese Station C. They had not beenpaying attention to the small changes that had been taking place each day, so theytook it for granted their Cheese would be there.They were unprepared for what they found.


“What! No Cheese?” Hem yelled. He continued yelling, “No Cheese? No Cheese?” asthough if he shouted loud enough someone would put back.“Who moved my Cheese?” he hollered.Finally, he put his hands on his hips, his face turned red, and he screamed at the top ofhis voice, “It’s not fair!”Haw just shook his head in disbelief. He, too, had counted on finding Cheese atCheese Station C. He stood there for a long time, frozen with chock. He was just notready for this.Hem was yelling something, but Haw didn’t want to hear it. He didn’t want to dealwith what was facing him, so he just turned everything out.The littlepeople’s behavior was not very attractive or productive but it wasunderstandable.Finding Cheese wasn’t easy, and it meant a great deal more to the littlepeople thanjust having enough of it to eat everyday.Finding Cheese was the littlepeoples’ way of getting what they though they needed tobe happy. They had their own ideas of what Cheese meant to them, depending ontheir taste.For some, finding Cheese was having material things. For others it was enjoying goodhealth, or developing a spiritual sense of well-being.For Haw, Cheese just meant feeling safe, having a loving family someday and livingin a cozy cottage on Cheddar Lane.To Hem, Cheese was becoming A Big Cheese in charge of others and owning a bighouse atop Camembert Hill.Because Cheese was important to them, the two littlepeople spent a long time tryingto decide what to do. All they could think trying to decide what to do. All they couldthink of was to keep looking around Cheeseless Station C to se of the Cheese wasreally gone.While Sniff and Scurry had quickly moved on, Hem and Haw continued to hem andhaw.They ranted and raved at the injustice of it all. Haw started to get depressed. Whatwould happen if the Cheese wasn’t there tomorrow? He had if the Cheese wasn’tthere tomorrow? He had made future plans based on this Cheese. The littlepeoplecouldn’t believe it. How could this have happened? No one had warned them. Itwasn’t right. It was not the way things were supposed to be.Hem and Haw went home that night hungry and discouraged. But before they left,Haw wrote on the wall:


The More Important Your Cheese Is To You The More You Want To Hold On To It.The next day Hem and Haw left their homes, and returned to Cheese Station C again,where they still expected, somehow, to find their Cheese.The situation hadn’t changed, the Cheese was no longer there. The littlepeople didn’tknow what to do. Hem and Haw just stood there, immobilized like two statues.Haw shut his eyes as tight as he could and put his hands over his ears. He just wantedto block everything out. He didn’t want to know the Cheese supply had graduallybeen getting smaller. He believed it had been moved all of a sudden.Hem analyzed the situation over and over and eventually his complicated brain withits huge belief system took hold. “Why did they do this to me?” he demanded.“What’s really going on here?”Finally Haw opened his eyes, looked around and said, “By the way, where are Sniffand Scurry? Do you think they know something we don’t?”Hem scoffed, “What would they know?”Hem continued, “They’re just simple mice. They just respond to what happens. We’relittlepeople. We’re special. We should be able to figure this out. And, besides, wedeserve better.”“This should not happen to us, or if it does, we should at least get some benefits.”“Why should we get benefits?” Haw asked.“Because we’re entitled,” Hem claimed.


“Entitled to what?” Haw wanted to know.“We’re entitled to our Cheese.”“Why?” Haw asked.“Because, we didn’t cause this problem,” Hem said. “Somebody else did this and weshould get something out of it.”Haw suggested, “Maybe we should stop analyzing the situation so much and just getgoing and find some New Cheese.”“Oh no,” Hem argued. “I’m going to get to the bottom of this.”While Hem and Haw were still trying to decide what to do, Sniff and Scurry werealready on their way. They went further into the maze, up and down corridors,looking for cheese in every Cheese Station they could find.They didn’t think of anything else but finding New Cheese.They didn’t find any for sometime until they finally went into an area of the mazewhere they had never been before: Cheese Station N.They squealed with delight. They found what they had been looking for a great supplyof New Cheese.They could hardly believe their eyes. It was the biggest store of cheese the mice hadever seen.In the meantime, Hem and Haw were still back in Cheese Station C evaluating theirsituation. They were now suffering from the effects of having no Cheese. They werebecoming frustrated and angry and were blaming each other for the situation theywere in.Now and then Haw thought about his mice buddies, Sniff and Scurry, and wonderedof they had found any cheese yet. He believed they might be having a hard time, asrunning through the maze usually involved some uncertainty. But he also knew that itwas likely to only last for a while.Sometimes, Haw would imagine Sniff and Scurry finding New Cheese and enjoyingit. He thought about how good it would be for him to be out on an adventure in themaze, and to find fresh New Cheese. He could almost taste it.The more clearly Haw saw the image of himself finding and enjoying the NewCheese, the more he saw himself leaving Cheese Station C.“Let’s go!” he exclaimed, all of a sudden.


“No,” Hem quickly responded. “I like it here. It’s comfortable. It’s what I know.Besides it’s dangerous out there.”“No, it isn’t,” Haw argued. “We’ve run through many parts of the maze before, andwe can do it again.”“I’m getting too old for that,” Hem said. “And I’m afraid I’m not interested in gettinglost and making a fool of myself. Are you?”With that, Haw’s fear of falling returned and his hope of finding New Cheese faded.So everyday, the littlepeople continued to do what they had done before. They went toCheese Station C, found no Cheese, and returned home, carrying their worries andfrustrations with them.They tried to deny what was happening, but found it harder to get to sleep, had lessenergy the next day, and were becoming irritable.Their homes were not the nurturing places they once were. The littlepeople haddifficulty sleeping and were having nightmares about not finding any Cheese.But Hem and Haw still returned to Cheese Station C and waited there everyday.Hem said, “You know, if we just work harder we'll find that nothing has reallychanged that much. The Cheese is probably nearby. Maybe they just hid it behind thewall.”The next day, Hem and Haw returned with tools. Hem held the chisel while Hawbanged on the hammer until they made a hole in the wall of Cheese Station C. Theypeered inside but found no Cheese.They were disappointed but believed they could solve the problem. So they startedearlier, stayed longer, and worked harder. But after a while, all they had was a largehole in the wall.Haw was beginning to realize the difference between activity and productivity.“Maybe,” Hem said, “we should just sit here and see what happens. Sooner or laterthey have to put the Cheese back.”Haw wanted to believe that. So each day he went home to rest and returnedreluctantly with Hem to Cheese Station C. But Cheese never reappeared.By now the littlepeople were growing weak from hunger and stress. Haw was gettingtired of just waiting for their situation to improve. He began to see that the longer theystayed in their Cheeseless situation, the worse off they would be.Haw knew they were losing their edge.


Finally, one day Haw began laughing at himself. “Haw, haw, look at me. I keep doingthe same things over and over again and wonder why things don't get better. If thiswasn't so ridiculous, it would be even funnier.”Haw did not like the idea of having to run through the maze again, because he knewhe would get lost and have no idea where he would find any Cheese. But he had tolaugh at his folly when he saw what his fear was doing to him.He asked Hem, “Where did we put our jogging suits and running shoes?” It took along time to find them because they had put everything away when they found theirCheese at Cheese Station C, thinking they wouldn't be needing them anymore.As Hem saw his friend getting into his running gear, he said, “You're not really goingout into the maze again, are you? Why don't you just wait here with me until they putthe Cheese back?”“Because, you just don't get it,” Haw said. “I didn't want to see it either, but now Irealize they're never going to put the Old Cheese back. That was yesterday's Cheese.It's time to find New Cheese.”Hem argued, “But what if there is no Cheese out there? Or even if there is, what ifyou don't find it?”“I don't know,” Haw said. He had asked himself those same questions too many timesand started to feel the fears again that kept him where he was.Then he thought about finding New Cheese and all the good things that came with itand gathered his courage.“Sometimes,” Haw said, “things change and they are never the same again. This lookslike one, of those times, Hem. That's life! Life moves on. And so should we.”Haw looked at his emaciated companion and tried to talk sense to him, but Hem's fearhad turned into anger and he wouldn't listen.Haw didn't mean to be rude to his friend, but he had to laugh at how silly they bothlooked.As Haw prepared to leave, he started to feel more alive, knowing that he was finallyable to laugh at himself, let go and move on.He announced, “It's maze time!”Hem didn't laugh and he didn't respond.Haw picked up a small, sharp rock and wrote a serious thought on the wall for Hem tothink about. As was his custom, Haw even drew a picture of cheese around it, hopingit would help Hem to smile, lighten up, and go after the New Cheese. But Hem didn'twant to see it. It read:


If You Do Not Change, You Can Become Extinct.Then, Haw stuck his head out and peered anxiously into the maze. He thought abouthow he'd gotten himself into this cheeseless situation.He had believed that there may not be any Cheese in the maze, or he may not find it.Such fearful beliefs were immobilizing and killing him.Haw smiled. He knew Hem was wondering, “Who moved my Cheese?” but Haw waswondering, “Why didn't I get up and move with the Cheese sooner?”As he started out into the maze, Haw looked back to where he had come from and feltits comfort. He could feel himself being drawn back into familiar territory - eventhough he hadn't found Cheese there for some time.Haw became more anxious and wondered if he really wanted to go out into the maze.He wrote a saying on the wall ahead of him and stared at it for some time: What Would You Do If You Weren’t Afraid?


He thought about it.He knew sometimes some fear can be good. When you are afraid things are going toget worse if you don't do something, it can prompt you into action. But it is not goodwhen you are so afraid that it keeps you from doing anything.He looked to his right, to the part of the maze where he had never been, and felt thefear.Then, he took a deep breath, turned right into the maze, and jogged slowly, into theunknown.As he tried to find his way, Haw worried, at first, that he might have waited too longin Cheese Station C. He hadn't had any Cheese for so long that he was now weak. Ittook him longer and it was more painful than usual to get through the maze. Hedecided that if he ever got the chance again, he would adapt to change sooner. Itwould make things easier.Then, Haw smiled a weak smile as he thought, “Better late than never.”During the next several days, Haw found a little Cheese here and there, but nothingthat lasted very long. He had hoped to find enough Cheese to take some back to Hemand encourage him to come out into the maze.But Haw didn't feel confident enough yet. He had to admit, he found it confusing inthe maze. Things seemed to have changed since the last time he was out here.Just when he thought he was getting ahead, he would get lost in the corridors. Itseemed his progress was two steps forward and one step backwards. It was achallenge, but he had to admit that being back in the maze, hunting for Cheese, wasn'tnearly as bad as he feared it might be.As time went on he began to wonder if it was realistic for him to expect to find NewCheese. He wondered if he had bitten off more than he could chew. Then he laughed,realizing that he had nothing to chew on at the moment.Whenever he started to get discouraged he reminded himself that what he was doing,as uncomfortable as it was at the moment, was in reality much better than staying inthe Cheeseless situation. He was taking control, rather than simply letting thingshappen to him.Then he reminded himself, if Sniff and Scurry could move on, so could he! Later, as Haw looked back on things, he realized that the Cheese at Cheese Station Chad not just disappeared overnight, as he had once thought. The amount of Cheese that had been there toward the end had been getting smaller, and what was left had grown old. It didn't taste as good.


Mold may even have begun to grow on the Old Cheese, although he hadn't noticed it.He had to admit however, that if he had wanted to, he probably could have seen whatwas coming. But he didn't. Haw now realized that the change probably would not have taken him by surprise if he had been watching what was happening all along and if he had anticipated change. Maybe that's what Sniff and Scurry had been doing. He stopped for a rest and wroteon the wall of the maze: Smell The Cheese Often So You Know When It Is Getting Old. Sometime later, after not finding Cheese for what seemed like a long time, Hawfinally came across a huge Cheese Station which looked promising. When he went inside, however, he was most disappointed to discover that the Cheese station was empty.“This empty feeling has happened to me too often,” he thought. He felt like giving up. Haw was losing his physical strength. He knew he was lost and was afraid he would not survive. He thought about turning around and heading back to Cheese Station C.At least, if he made it back, and Hem was still there, Haw wouldn't be alone. Then he asked himself the same question, again: “What would I do if I weren't afraid?”He was afraid more often than he liked to admit, even to himself. He wasn't always sure what he was afraid of, but, in his weakened condition, he knew now he was simply fearful of going on alone. Haw didn't know it, but he was running behind because he was weighed down by fearful be liefs. Haw wondered if Hem had moved on, or if he was still paralyzed by his fears. Then, Haw remembered the times when he had felt his best in the maze. It was when he was moving along.


He wrote on the wall, knowing it was as much a reminder to himself as it was a marking for his buddy Hem hopefully to follow: Smell The Cheese Often So You Know When It Is Getting Old. Haw looked down the dark passageway and was aware of his fear. What lay ahead? Was it empty? Or worse, were there dangers lurking? He began to imagine all kinds of frightening things that could happen to him. He was scaring himself to death. Then he laughed at himself. He realized his fears were making things worse. So hedid what he would do if he wasn't afraid. He moved in a new direction. As he started running down the dark corridor he began to smile. Haw didn't realize it yet, but he was discovering what nourished his soul. He was letting go and trusting what lay ahead for him, even though he did not know exactly what it was. To his surprise, Haw started to enjoy himself more and more. “Why do I feel so good?” he wondered. “I don't have any Cheese and I don't know where I am going.”Before long, he knew why he felt good. He stopped to write again on the wall: When You Move Beyond Your Fear, You Feel Free.


Haw realized he had been held captive by his own fear. Moving in a new directionhad freed him. Now he felt the cool breeze that was blowing in this part of the maze and it was refreshing. He took in some deep breaths and felt invigorated by the movement. Once he had gotten past his fear, it turned out to be more enjoyable than he once believed it could be. Haw hadn't felt this way for a long time. He had almost forgotten how much fun it was. To make things even better, Haw started to paint a picture in his mind. He saw him self in great realistic detail, sitting in the middle of a pile of all his favoritecheeses-from Cheddar to Brie! He saw himself eating the many cheeses he liked, and he enjoyed what he saw. Then he imagined how much he would enjoy all their great tastes. The more clearly he saw the image of New Cheese, the more real it became, and the more he could sense that he was going to find it. He wrote: Imagining Myself Enjoying New Cheese Even Before I find It, Leads Me To It.“Why didn't I do this before?” Haw asked himself. Then he raced through the maze with greater strength and agility. Before long he spotted a Cheese Station and became excited as he noticed little pieces of New Cheesenear the entrance. They were types of Cheeses he had never seen before, but they looked great. He tried them and found that they were delicious. He ate most of the New Cheese bits that were available and put a few in his pocket to have later and perhaps share with Hem. He began to regain his strength.


He entered the Cheese Station with great excitement. But, to his dismay, he found it was empty. Someone had already been there and had left only the few bits of New Cheese. He realized that if he had moved sooner, he would very likely have found a good deal of New Cheese here. Haw decided to go back and see if Hem was ready to join him. As he retraced his steps, he stopped and wrote on the wall: The quicker You Let Go Of Old Cheese, The Sooner You Find New Cheese. After a while Haw made his way back to Cheese Station C and found Hem. He offered Hem bits of New Cheese, but was turned down. Hem appreciated his friend's gesture but said, “I don't think I would like New Cheese. It's not what I'm used to. I want my own Cheese back and I'm not going to change until I get what I want.”Haw just shook his head in disappointment and reluctantly went back out on his own. As he returned to the farthest point he had reached in the maze, he missed his friend, but realized he liked what he was discovering. Even before he found what he hoped would be a great supply of New Cheese, if ever, he knew that what made him happy wasn't just having Cheese. He was happy when he wasn't being run by his fear. He liked what he was doing now. Knowing this, Haw didn't feel as weak as he did when he stayed in Cheese Station Cwith no Cheese. Just realizing he was not letting his fear stop him and knowing that he had taken a new direction nourished him and gave him strength. Now he felt that it was just a question of time before he found what he needed. In fact, he sensed he had already found what he was looking for. He smiled as he realized:


It Is Safer To Search In The Maze Than Remain In A Cheese less Situation. Haw realized again, as he had once before, that what you are afraid of is never as badas what you imagine. The fear you let build up in your mind is worse than the situation that actually exists. He'd been so afraid of never finding New Cheese that he didn't even want to start looking. But since starting his journey he had found enough Cheese in the corridors to keep him going. Now he looked forward to finding more. Just looking ahead was becoming exciting. His old thinking had been clouded by his worries and fears. He used to think about not having enough Cheese, or not having it last as long as he wanted. He used to think more about what could go wrong than what could go right. But that had changed in the days since he had left Cheese Station C.He used to believe that Cheese should never be moved and that change wasn't right. Now he realized it was natural for change to continually Occur, whether you expect itor not. Change could surprise you only if you didn't expect it and weren't looking forit. When he realized he had changed his beliefs, he paused to write on the wall:


Old Beliefs Do Not Lead You To New Cheese. Haw hadn't found any Cheese yet but, as he ran through the maze, he thought about what he had already learned. Haw now realized that his new beliefs were encouraging new behaviors. He was behaving differently than when he kept returning to the same cheese less station. He knew when you change what you believe, you change what you do. You can believe that a change will harm you and resist it. Or you can believe that finding New Cheese will help you to embrace the change. It all depends on what you choose to believe. He wrote on the wall: When You See That You Can Find And Enjoy New Cheese, You Change Course. Haw knew he would be in better shape now if he had embraced the change much sooner and left Cheese Station C earlier. He would feel stronger in body and spirit and


he could have coped better with the challenge of finding New Cheese. In fact, he probably would have found it by now if he had expected change, rather than was ting time denying that the change had already taken place. He gathered his will and decided to keep proceeding into the newer parts of the maze. He found little bits of Cheese here and there and began to regain his strength and confidence.As he thought back on where he had come from, Haw was glad he had written on thewall in many places. He trusted it would serve as a marked trail for Hem to follow through the maze, if he chose to leave Cheese Station C.He just hoped he was heading in the right direction. He thought about the possibility that Hem would read The Handwriting On The Wall and find his way. He wrote on the wall what he had been thinking about for some time: Noticing Small Changes Early Helps You Adapt To The Bigger Changes That Are To Come.By now, Haw had let go of the past and was adapting to the future. He continued on through the maze with greater strength and speed. And before long, it happened. When it seemed like he had been in the maze forever, his journey - or at least this part of his journey - ended quickly and happily. Haw found New Cheese at Cheese Station N!When he went inside, he was startled by what he saw. Piled high everywhere was the greatest supply of Cheese he had ever seen. He didn't recognize all that he saw, assome kinds of Cheese were new to him.


Then he wondered for a moment whether it was real or just his imagination, until hesaw his old friends Sniff and Scurry. Sniff welcomed Haw with a nod of his head, and Scurry waved his paw. Their fatlittle bellies showed that they had been here for some time. Haw quickly said his hellos and soon took bites of everyone of his favorite Cheeses. He pulled off his shoes and jogging suit and folded them neatly nearby in case he needed them again. Then he jumped into the New Cheese. When he had eaten his fill, he lifted a piece of fresh Cheese and made a toast. “Hooray for Change!”As Haw enjoyed the New Cheese, he reflected on what he had learned. He realized that when he had been afraid to change he had been holding on to the illusion of Old Cheese that was no longer there. So what was it that made him change? Was it the fear of starving to death? Haw thought, “Well, that helped.”Then he laughed and realized that he had started to change as soon as he had learned to laugh at himself and at what he had been doing wrong. He realized the fastest way to change is to laugh at your own folly - then you can let go and quickly move on. He knew he had learned something useful about moving on from his mice buddies, Sniff and Scurry. They kept life simple. They didn't overanalyze or overcomplicatethings. When the situation changed and the Cheese had been moved, they change dand moved with the Cheese. He would remember that. Then Haw used his wonderful brain to do what little people do better than mice. He reflected on the mistakes he had made in the past and used them to plan for his future. He knew that you could learn to deal with change:You could be more aware of the need to keep things simple, be flexible, and movequickly. You did not need to overcomplicate matters or confuse yourself with fearful beliefs. You could notice when the little changes began so that you would be better prepared for the big change that might be coming. He knew he needed to adapt faster, for if you do not adapt in time, you might as wellnot adapt at all. He had to admit that the biggest inhibitor to change lies within yourself, and that nothing gets better until you change.Perhaps most important of all, he realized that there is always New Cheese out therewhether you recognize it at the time or not. And that you are rewarded with it whenyou go past your fear and enjoy the adventure.


He knew some fear should be respected, as it can keep you out of real danger. But herealized most of his fears were irrational and had kept him from changing when heneeded to change. He didn't like it at the time, but he knew that the change had turned out to be ablessing in disguise as it led him to find better Cheese. He had even found a better part of himself. As Haw recalled what he had learned, he thought about his friend Hem. He wondered if Hem had read any of the sayings Haw had written on the wall at Cheese Station Cand throughout the maze. Had Hem ever decided to let go and move on? Had he ever entered the maze anddiscovered what could make his life better? Haw thought about going back again to Cheese Station C to see if he could find Hem- assuming that Haw could find his way back there. If he found Hem, he thought hemight be able to show him how to get out of his predicament. But Haw realized that he had already tried to get his friend to change. Hem had to find his own way, beyond his comforts and past his fears. No one elsecould do it for him, or talk him into it. He somehow had to see the advantage ofchanging himself. Haw knew he had left a trail for Hem and that he could find his way, if he could justread The Handwriting On The Wall.He went over and wrote down a summary of what he had learned on the largest wallof Cheese Station N. He drew a large piece of cheese around all the insights he hadbecome aware of, and smiled as he looked at what he had learned:


THE HANDWRITING On THE WALL Change Happens They Keep M oving The Cheese Anticipate Change GetReady For The Cheese To M ove Monitor ChangeSm ellThe Cheese Often So You Know W hen ItIs Getting O ld Adapt To Change QuicklyThe Quicker You LetGo OfOld Cheese,The Sooner You Can Enjoy N ew Cheese Change M ove W ith The Cheese Enjoy Change! Savor The Adventure And Enjoy The Taste OfN ew Cheese! Be Ready To Change Quickly And Enjoy It Again They Keep M oving The Cheese


Haw realized how far he had come since he had been with Hem in Cheese Station C,but knew it would be easy for him to slip back if he got too comfortable. Each day heinspected Cheese Station N to see what the condition of his Cheese was. He wasgoing to do whatever he could to avoid being surprised by unexpected change.While Haw still had a great supply of Cheese, he often went out into the maze andexplored new areas to stay in touch with what was happening around him. He knew itwas safer to be aware of his real choices than to isolate himself in his comfort zone.Then, Haw heard what he thought was the sound of movement out in the maze. As thenoise grew louder, he realized that someone was coming.Could it be that Hem was arriving? Was he about to turn the corner?Haw said a little prayer and hoped - as he had many times before - that maybe, at last,his friend was finally able to… Move With The Cheese And Enjoy It!


A Discussion Later That Same DayWhen Michael finished telling the story, he looked around the room and saw his former classmates smiling at him.Several thanked him and said they got a good deal out of the story. Nathan asked the group, “What would you think of getting together later and maybediscussing it?”Most of them said they would like to talk about it, and so they arranged to meet laterfor a drink before dinner. That evening, as they gathered in a hotel lounge, they began to kid each other aboutfinding their “Cheese” and seeing themselves in the maze. Then Angela asked the group good-naturedly, “So, who were you in the story? Sniff,Scurry, Hem or Haw?”Carlos answered, “Well, I was thinking about that this afternoon. I clearly remember atime before I had my sporting goods business, when I had a rough encounter withchange.“I wasn't Sniff - I didn't sniff out the situation and see the change early. And Icertainly wasn't Scurry - I didn't go into action immediately.“I was more like Hem, who wanted to stay in familiar territory. The truth is, I didn't want to deal with the change. I didn't even want to see it.”Michael, who felt like no time had passed since he and Carlos were close friends in school, asked, “What are we talking about here, buddy?”Carlos said, “An unexpected change of jobs.”Michael laughed, “You were fired?”“Well let's just say I didn't want to go out looking for New Cheese I thought I had agood reason why change shouldn't happen to me So, I was pretty upset at the time.”Some of their former classmates who had been quiet in the beginning felt morecomfortable now and spoke up, including Frank, who had gone into the military.“Hem reminds me of a friend of mine,” Frank said. “His department was closingdown, but he didn't want to see it. They kept relocating his people. We all tried to talk to him about the many other opportunities that existed in the company for those who wanted to be flexible, but he didn't think he had to change. He was the only one who was surprised when his department closed. Now he's having a hard time adjusting tothe change he didn't think should happen.”


Jessica said, “I didn't think it should happen to me either, but my 'Cheese' has beenmoved more than once.”Many in the group laughed, except Nathan.“Maybe that's the whole point,” Nathan said. “Change happens to all of us.”He added, “I wish my family had heard the Cheese story before this. Unfortunatelywe didn't want to see the changes coming in our business, and now it's too late - we're having to close many of our stores.”That surprised many in the group, because they thought Nathan was lucky to be in asecure business he could depend on, year after year.“What happened?” Jessica wanted to know.“Our chain of small stores suddenly became old fashioned when the mega-store cameto town with its huge inventory and low prices. We just couldn't compete with that.“I can see now that instead of being like Sniff and Scurry, we were like Hem. Westayed where we were and didn't change. We tried to ignore what was happening andnow we are in trouble. We could have taken a lesson or two from Haw.”Laura, who had become a successful business-woman, had been listening, but hadsaid very little until now. “I thought about the story this afternoon too,” she said. “Iwondered how I could be more like Haw and see what I'm doing wrong; laugh atmyself; change and do better.”She said, “I'm curious. How many here are afraid of change?” No one responded, soshe suggested, “How about a show of hands?”Only one hand went up. “Well, it looks like we've got one honest person in ourgroup!” she said. And then continued, “Maybe you'll like this next question better. How many here think other people are afraid of change?” Everyone raised their hands. Then they all started laughing.“What does that tell us?” “Denial,” Nathan answered. Michael admitted, “Sometimes we're not even aware that we're afraid. I know I wasn't. When I first heard the story, I loved the question, 'What would you do if you weren't afraid?’”Then Jessica added, “Well, what I got from the story is that change is going to happen- whether I'm afraid of it, or whether I like it, or not.“I remember years ago when our company was selling sets of encyclopedia books. One person tried to tell us that we should put our whole encyclopedia on a single


computer disk and sell it for a fraction of the cost. It would cost us so much less tomanufacture and so many more people could afford it. But we all resisted.”“Why did you resist?” Nathan asked.“Because, we believed then that the backbone of our business was our large sales force, who called on people door-to-door. Keeping our sales force depended on the big commissions they earned from the high price of our product. We had been doing this successfully for a long time and thought it would go on forever.” “It was your ‘Cheese’,” Nathan said.“Yes, and we wanted to hang on to it. “When I think back on what happened to us, Isee that it's not just that they 'moved the Cheese,' but that the 'Cheese' has a life of itsown and eventually runs out.“Anyway, we didn't change. But a competitor did and our sales fell badly. We've beengoing through a difficult time. Now, another big technological change is happening in the industry and no one at the company seems to want to deal with it. It doesn't lookgood. I think I could be out of a job soon.”“It's maze time!” Carlos called out. Everyone laughed, including Jessica. Carlos turned to Jessica and said, “It's good that you can laugh at yourself.”Frank offered, “That's what I got out of the story. I tend to take myself too seriously. Inoticed how Haw changed when he could finally laugh at himself and at what he was doing. No wonder he was called Haw.”Angela asked, “Do you think that Hem ever changed and found New Cheese?”Elaine said, “I think he did.” “I don't,” Cory said. “Some people never change and they pay a price for it. I see people like Hem in my medical practice. They feel entitled to their 'Cheese.' They feel like victims when it's taken away and blame others. They get sicker than people who let go and move on.”Then Nathan said quietly, as though he was talking to himself, “I guess the questionis, 'What do we need to let go of and what do we need to move on to?'”No one said anything for a while.“I must admit,” Nathan said, “I saw what was happening in other parts of the country, but I hoped it wouldn't affect us. I guess it's a lot better to initiate change while you can than it is to try to react and adjust to it. Maybe we should move our own Cheese.” “What do you mean?” Frank asked.


Nathan answered, “I can't help but wonder where we would be today if we had soldthe real estate under all our old stores and built a great modern store to compete with the best of them.”Laura said, “Maybe that's what Haw meant when he wrote on the wall 'Savor the adventure and move with the Cheese.'”Frank said, “I think some things shouldn't change. For example, I want to hold on tomy basic values. But I realize now that I would be better off if I had moved with the'Cheese' a lot sooner in my life.”“Well, Michael, it was a nice little story,” Richard, the class skeptic, said, “but howdid you actually put it into use in your company?”The group didn't know it yet, but Richard was experiencing some changes himself.Recently separated from his wife, he was now trying to balance his career with raisinghis teenagers.Michael replied, “You know, I thought my job was just to manage the daily problemsas they came up when I should have been looking ahead and paying attention tow here we were going.“And boy did I manage those problems - twenty-four hours a day. I wasn't a lot of funto be around. I was in a rat race and I couldn't get out.“However, after I first heard the story of 'Who Moved My Cheese?' and saw how Haw changed,” Michael continued, “1 realized that my job was to paint a picture of'New Cheese.' And to do it so clearly and realistically that I and the other people I worked with could all enjoy changing and succeeding together.”“That's interesting,” Angela said. “Because, to me, the most powerful part of the story was when Haw ran past his fear and painted a picture in his mind of finding 'NewCheese.' Running through the maze became less fearful and more enjoyable. And heeventually got a better deal.”Richard, who had been frowning during the discussion, said, “My manager's beentelling me our company needs to change. I think what she's really telling me is that I need to, but I haven't wanted to hear it. I guess I never really knew what the 'NewCheese' was that she was trying to move us to. Or how I could gain from it.”A slight grin crossed Richard's face as he said, “1 must admit I like this idea of seeing'New Cheese' and imagining yourself enjoying it. It lightens everything up. It lessensthe fear and gets you more interested in making the change happen.“Maybe I could use this at home,” he added. “My children seem to think that nothingin their lives should ever change. They're angry. I guess they're afraid of what the future holds. Maybe I haven't painted a realistic picture of 'New Cheese' for them. Probably because I don't see it myself.”The group was quiet as several people thought about their own family life.


“Well,” Elaine said, “most people here are talking about jobs, but as I listened to the story, I thought about my personal life. I think my current relationship is 'Old Cheese 'that has some pretty serious mold on it.”Cory laughed in agreement. “Me too. I probably need to let go of a bad relationship.”Angela countered, “Or, perhaps the 'Old Cheese' is just old behavior. What we really need to let go of is the behavior that keeps causing our bad relationship. And then move on to a better way of thinking and acting.” “Ouch!” Cory reacted. “Good point. The New Cheese is a new relationship with the same person.”Richard said, “I'm beginning to think there is more to this than I thought. I like the idea of letting go of old behavior instead of letting go of the relationship. Repeating the same behavior will just get you the same results.“Instead of changing jobs, maybe I should be one of the people helping my company change. I'd probably have a better job by now if I did.”Then Becky, who lived in another city but had returned for the reunion, said, “As I was listening to the story and to everyone's comments here, I've had to laugh at myself. I've been like Hem for so long, hemming and hawing and afraid of change. I didn't realize how many other people did this as well. I'm afraid I've passed it on to my children without even knowing it. “As I think about it, I realize change really can lead you to a new and better place, although you're afraid it won't at the time. “I remember a time when our son was a sophomore in high school. My husband's job required us to move from Illinois to Vermont and our son was upset because he had to leave his friends. He was a star swimmer and the high school in Vermont had no swim team. So, he was angry with us for making him move.“As it turned out, he fell in love with the Vermont mountains, took up skiing, skied onhis college team and now lives happily in Colorado.“If we had all enjoyed this Cheese story together, over a cup of hot chocolate, we could have saved our family a lot of stress.”Jessica said, “I'm going home to tell my family this story. I'll ask my children who they think I am - Sniff, Scurry, Hem or Haw - and who they feel they are. We could talk about what we feel our family's Old Cheese is and what the New Cheese could be.” “That's a good idea,” Richard said. Frank then commented, “I think I'm going to be more like Haw and move with the Cheese and enjoy it! And I'm going to pass this story along to my friends who are


worried about leaving the military and what the change will mean to them. It couldlead to some interesting discussions.”Michael said, “Well, that's how we improved our business. We had several discussions about what we got from the Cheese story and how we could apply it to our own situation. “It was great because we had language that was fun for us to use to talk about how we were dealing with change. It was very effective, especially as it spread deeper into the company.” “How so?” Nathan asked.“Well, the further we went into our organization, the more people we found who felt they had less power. They were understandably more afraid of what the change imposed from above might do to them. So they resisted change.“In short, a change imposed is a change opposed.“I only wished I'd heard the Cheese story sooner,” Michael added.“How come?” Carlos asked. “Because by the time we got around to addressing the changes, our business had already fallen off so badly that we had to let people go, including some good friends. It was hard on all of us. However, practically everyone, those who left and those who stayed, said the Cheese story helped them see things differently and cope better.“Those who had to go out and look for a new job said it was hard at first but recalling the story was a great help to them.”Angela asked, “What helped them most?”Michael replied, “After they got past their fear, they told me the best thing was realizing that there was New Cheese out there just waiting to be found! “They said holding a picture of New Cheese in their minds made them feel better, and so they did better in job interviews. Several got better jobs.”Laura asked “What about the people who remained in your company?” “Well,” Michael said, “instead of complaining about the changes that were happening, people now said, 'They just moved our Cheese. Let's look for the New Cheese.' It saved a lot of time and reduced stress. “Before long, the people who had been resisting saw the advantage of changing. They even helped bring about change.”Cory said, “Why do you think that happened?” “I think a lot of it had to do with the kind of peer pressure that can exist in a company.


“What happens in most organizations you've been in when a change is announced by top management? Do most people say the change is a great idea or a bad idea?” “A bad idea,” Frank answered. “Yes,” Michael agreed. “Why?”Carlos said, “Because people want things to stay the same and they think the change will be bad for them. When one smart person says the change is a bad idea, others say the same.” “Yes, they may not really feel that way,” Michael said, “but they agree in order to look smart as well. That's the sort of peer pressure that fights change in any organization. ”Becky added, “In families, the same thing can happen between parents and children.”Then she asked, “So how were things different for you after people heard the Cheese story?”Michael said simply, “People changed because no one wanted to look like Hem!”Everyone laughed including Nathan, who said, “That's a good point. No one in my family would want to look like Hem. They might even change. Why didn't you tell us this story at our last reunion? This could really work.”Michael offered one last thought. “When we saw how well it worked for us, we passed the story along to people we wanted to do business with-knowing their organizations were also dealing with change. We suggested we might be their 'New Cheese,' that is, better partners for them to succeed with. It led to new business.”That gave Jessica several ideas and reminded her that she had some early sales calls in the morning. She looked at her watch and said, “Well, it's time for me to leave this Cheese Station and find some New Cheese.”The group laughed and began saying their good-byes. Many of them wanted to continue the conversation but needed to leave. As they left, they thanked Michael again. He said, “I'm very glad you found the story so useful and I hope that you will have the opportunity to share it with others soon." the end.